<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>50 Years Later</title>
    <description>A Daily Texan feature story.</description>
    <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 08:51:58 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 08:51:58 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Experts still disagree on role of Tower shooter&#39;s brain tumor</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/brain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;In the years following the shooting, experts have debated the affect a brain tumor had on his mental health.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Illustration by Melanie Westfall, Daily Texan Staff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart, strong, talented and popular, the young Charles Whitman seemed, outwardly, like a poster child for the “all-American boy” stereotype.
But as the sandy-haired boy grew up into a tall, athletic ex-Marine, beneath his mop of blond hair, something else was also growing. A brain tumor, nestled between his thalamus, hypothalamus and amygdala, developed quietly to the size of a pecan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his 25th year, Whitman began to complain of headaches, a severe, persistent pain that he later described as “tremendous.” He wrote increasingly troubled journal entries detailing his mental state: “Recently (I cannot recall when it started) I have been a victim of many unusual and irrational thoughts.” He paid a visit to the campus mental health center complaining of violent impulses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, one sweltering August day in 1966, Whitman did something no one expected: He climbed to the top of the UT tower with a sawed-off shotgun, and began shooting. His 96-minute reign of terror killed 14 people on campus and injured 31 more, and only ended when he was killed by Austin police.
Whitman’s suicide note requested an autopsy to examine his brain, because he was convinced it would show some “visible physical disorder.” The shooting — the deadliest college shooting until Virginia Tech in 2007 — left the nation in shock and clamoring for answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the initial autopsy was inconclusive about the role of the tumor in the shooting, a follow-up investigation by a group of scientists under a commission requested by governor John Connally showed it could have played a part in the events of that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The highly malignant brain tumor conceivably could have contributed to his inability to control his emotions and actions,” wrote Stuart Brown, an assistant professor of psychiatry at Baylor College of Medicine, in the initial 1966 report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all experts agree on whether the tumor affected Whitman’s thoughts and actions on that August day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Koenigs, an expert on brain lesions, said that the position of Whitman’s tumor — pressing against the amygdala — definitely had the potential to affect his mental state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amygdala is a region at the back of the brain involved in emotional regulation and regulation of responses such as fear and aggression. Koenigs said he has seen instances of tumors like Whitman’s which have affected patient’s’ entire personalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is unlikely that a tumor initiated some type of psychotic rage, but it could have tweaked his personality to be a bit more aggressive or a bit less empathetic,” Koenigs said. “It could certainly affect his emotional state, and it could certainly affect his body’s physiological responses to threat and healthy emotional responses related to aggression.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other scientists, like N. Bradley Keele, an associate professor at Baylor College of Medicine, takes a more skeptical point of view. Keele, who studies the amygdala, said that although the location of the tumor could have affected Whitman’s behavior, it is unlikely that it was the sole reason for his actions or even an important contributing factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes, he had an aggressive, malignant tumor in his temporal lobe that could have impacted his bizarre and violent behavior,” Keele said. “However, what is often overlooked is that he came from a very abusive home, and admitted to domestic violence with his own wife prior to stabbing her. I suspect his tumor was little more than ‘circumstantial.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view is shared by Gary Lavergne, author of the 1997 book “A Sniper in the Tower.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For 48 hours, [Whitman] made serial decisions in a correct order leading to the accomplishment of a goal,” Lavergne said. “To me his actions speak for themselves. If indeed a tumor or anything else took control of him and made him do something he didn’t want to do, when did this ‘seizure’ of sorts start?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lavergne hypothesized that Whitman’s violence was largely due to discontent with his situation and resentment towards his family, and after further research, said he even doubts the existence of the tumor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“After my book came out, I met two doctors who didn’t believe he had a brain tumor at all,” Lavergne said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s sophisticated brain imaging technology could allow a more accurate look into Whitman’s brain, but Whitman’s brain has been reported by some media outlets as being among the “missing” brains that UT employees disposed of in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if it were possible to pinpoint the effects of the tumor of Whitman’s actions, the question would still remain whether or not the answer should change the public’s perception of him. If it were proven that the tumor was a cause, would Whitman himself be less to blame?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What does it mean when somebody’s brain changes?” asked David Eagleman, a scientist who studies the intersection between neuroscience and law.  “This really challenges us to think about criminality in a different way because you don’t choose your genetics, you don’t choose your childhood experiences, your family of origin, your neighborhood, you don’t choose any of this stuff — and yet this is the stuff, your genetics plus your experiences, that makes you who you are. None of us would choose to have a brain tumor.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eagleman said that although the tumor could have been partly responsible for Whitman’s actions, it would be unlikely to change the public’s perception of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“His crime was so horrific — he killed his wife and mother the night before and shot all these random strangers — I think society would not forgive him,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eagleman runs the Center for Science and Law, a nonprofit dedicated to exploring the boundaries between biological causes of crimes and how those crimes are dealt with under the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What stresses and strains us as people is knowing on the one hand that we are biological creatures, and knowing on the other hand that acts of violence like his are so deep and awful that they feel unforgivable,” he said. “We live in that tension.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Whitman-Tumor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Whitman-Tumor.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>sniper</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Play deprivation seen as one of the factors that led to UT tower shooting in 1966</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/institute.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stuart Brown&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption-photo&quot;&gt;Psychiatrist Stuart Brown was part of a 1966 committee that delivered a report on the life of Charles Whitman to then-Texas Gov. John Connally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Photo Courtesy of Stuart Brown&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After studying the life of UT Tower shooter Charles Whitman, one psychiatrist found that play deprivation as a child and an overbearing father may have driven him to carry out the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the shooting, which left 31 people wounded and 15 dead, then-Gov. John Connally commissioned a study of Whitman’s life and what might have caused him to commit the crime. The commission consisted of more than 30 experts including psychiatrists, neurosurgeons and pathologists who studied Whitman’s life and a tumor that was found in his brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pathology experts concluded “the data obtained provide no evidence that [Whitman] had a clinical neurological abnormality, and there is no evidence from the pathological reports that [a tumor] interrupted pathways leading to detectable neurological signs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the psychiatrists on the commission believed Whitman’s relationship with his father was one of the factors that led to the massacre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Charles J. Whitman was deeply concerned over the chronic marital discord and recent separation of his parents,” reads the report. “He often had strong, variable, inconsistent feelings of hostility toward members of his family, particularly his father.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report also mentioned a particular episode from Whitman’s childhood when his father became aggressive at a family gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Charles A. Whitman insisted that his son play the piano for them,” the report said. “When the son experienced some difficulty in giving a perfect performance, his father threw a Coke bottle at him, striking him on the side of his head.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuart Brown, one of the commission’s psychiatrists, also noted Whitman’s previous knowledge of weaponry and the culminating tension he faced during his final months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whitman’s long developmental trajectory and [the lack of] healthy free play, combined with the repetitive family violence perpetrated by his father, his familiarity and excellence in weaponry, and the triggering events and stress over the last months of his life were also contributory [to his motives for the shooting],” Brown said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown, who founded the National Institute for Play, an organization created to study and raise awareness of the impact of play, said he was able to study Whitman’s entire life by interviewing his friends, family and gradeschool teachers. From this, Brown found that Whitman’s father had high expectations for his son, including a wish for Whitman to be president of the United States one day. These hopes from Whitman’s father interfered with him receiving the proper amount of play as a child, Brown said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hallie Speranza is a lecturer and master teacher at the Priscilla Pond Flawn Child and Family Laboratory, which allows students to interact with children and observe their development in problem-solving, self-esteem and self-control. She said play has a major impact on a lot of aspects of a child’s future, such as interacting with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s one place where, neurologically, we’re making connections that are important for our future problem-solving,” Speranza said. “It’s really important for building the intellect, really thinking about situations and problem-solving as opposed to being academic.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report found Whitman did not have the opportunity to develop these problem-solving skills at a young age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“[Whitman] seemed to achieve no sense of pleasure or feeling of mastery from learning a subject, and appeared always to be dissatisfied with himself whenever studying, with problem solving, or incompleting projects,” the report said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speranza, along with Brown, said children today are not getting enough play and interaction with other children, which can have lasting impacts on their futures. Speranza said the opportunity to play is being replaced with the need to be involved in academic-related activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At times when children have the opportunity to play,  there’s now more of a pressure to take on academic knowledge and skills,” Speranza said. “Sometimes it’s referred to as the push-down: all of the things that used to happen in first grade, now happen in kindergarten so those children are losing that time when they could really be interacting with other children and being creative.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Crosnoe, a UT sociology and psychology professor and expert in family, said lack of play, facilitated by his father, couldn’t have been the only driving force that led Whitman to the Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Parents have enormous effects — good and bad — on the kinds of adults their children turn out to be, both because of genetics, the environment that they create for them and how they parent them,” Crosnoe said. “However, when a clearly disturbed man commits mass murder, we need to refrain from trying to find a single reason for it. It is likely a lot more complicated than the parents he had, and it is certainly more complicated than a single thing that a parent did.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Whitman-Father.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Whitman-Father.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>sniper</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brackenridge Hospital: Locals come together in face of tragedy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/0801_AlbertLee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brackenridge Hospital&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Illustration by Albert Lee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On an uneventful Monday morning at Brackenridge Hospital, nurse Norma White sent her staff home early. They had already finished the day’s work, and with many of the doctors out of town, there was no need to keep them around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one by one, the same nurses she’d just sent home soon returned to the hospital. They’d seen reports of a sniper shooting people from the top of the University Tower and raced back to Brackenridge before the emergency room staff had been notified of any incoming victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the hospital, Dr. Robert Pape was in a meeting with their chief of staff when a call came in from the ER: “I need all the help I can get. There’s a nut on the UT campus shooting people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the shooter, a military-trained gunman named Charles Whitman, held a 96-minute “reign of terror” over the campus, the doctors and nurses got to work, preparing operating rooms and medical instruments for the urgent-care patients they were sure to receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-nine patients would be brought into the ER in the next hour and a half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I walked into the emergency room, and it was like a war zone,” White, a UT alumna who served as both operating room director and head intensive care nurse in 1966, said. “You saw people lying on stretchers with all these massive wounds, and I thought, ‘Oh my goodness, this is like something you would see on a battlefield.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it was soon all-hands-on-deck in the operating rooms, only one of Austin’s cardiothoracic surgeons was in town to treat victims with critical chest wounds. Two of the others, Dr. Pape said, were volunteering in Africa; another drove to Lubbock that morning, oblivious to the news of the shooting until he arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the surgeon opened chest after chest, he also had to keep his own health in mind. To manage his diabetes, nurses came by to feed him sweetened orange juice and milk during the hours-long surgeries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They were ready to do whatever was necessary,” Dr. Pape said. “They made do with what they had and they did a good job.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, some unanticipated recruits arrived. Without so much as a call, local doctors, from general practitioners to dermatologists, came to help. By the end of the day, the ER check-in sheet listed the names of nearly 60 volunteer doctors, Dr. Pape said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As doctors rushed in, they abandoned their cars in the ambulance driveway, their keys still in the ignition. A pileup of vehicles soon blocked the emergency room entrance, leaving civilians to clear them out of the way of the funeral home hearses that carried the shooting victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locals also lined up to donate blood to the victims, White said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The doctors and nurses worked until after midnight — more than 12 hours after the first bullets were fired — and many of the patients stayed in the hospital for weeks or, in some cases, months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the days before most hospitals had emergency rooms, Brackenridge was on the cutting edge, known as the only nearby trauma hospital. In the weeks before the shooting, everyone from interns to surgeons had run through their emergency protocol at a mock plane crash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of chaos or panic, Dr. Pape said that on the day of the shooting, the training kicked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Every year we wondered if we would have to use our emergency procedure, and then we had the opportunity to do it,” Dr. Pape said. “That really helped to solidify our response to the shooter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eleven of the patients brought to the hospital died that day or were already dead upon arrival. White credits the hospital’s trauma plans and the community’s support for saving the other 28 lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No matter their position, the citizens of Austin came together,” White said. “Everyone was working as hard and as fast as they could. You had no time to think about anything other than those patients.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/UMC-Brackenridge.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/UMC-Brackenridge.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>hero</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>‘Tower’ filmmakers shed light on humanity in moments of darkness</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/tower.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;(From left to right) Coordinating producer Hillary Pierce, director Keith Maitland and producer Megan Gilbride premiered their &amp;quot;Tower&amp;quot; documentary at the South By Southwest film festival this past spring. The documentary is set for a theatrical release on October 12th.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption-photo&quot;&gt;(From left to right) Coordinating producer Hillary Pierce, director Keith Maitland and producer Megan Gilbride premiered their “Tower” documentary at the South By Southwest film festival this past spring. The documentary is set for a theatrical release on October 12th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Photo by Joshua Guerra, Daily Texan Staff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Austin-based director Keith Maitland first learned of the Tower shooting from his seventh-grade Texas history teacher. The topic wasn’t part of the school’s curriculum, but the teacher, a UT alumna who witnessed the shooting, felt compelled to share her story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“From the moment she first told me about her experience at the shooting, I’ve always put myself in those shoes,” Maitland said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, Maitland came upon a Texas Monthly article featuring a collection of accounts from students, police officers and others who had found themselves caught in the crisis. Maitland had never heard their stories and didn’t want other accounts to go untold. So he went to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His curiosity eventually gave way to “Tower,” a documentary that tells the story of an attack that has largely faded from the public dialogue through the eyes of its survivors. Coordinating producer Hillary Pierce said the filmmakers reached out to eyewitnesses by putting out calls for stories and advertising on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was amazing how many people came forward because they’d never been asked to talk about it before,” Pierce said. “Just kind of putting that out there and saying, ‘We want to hear your story’ — people responded.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gathering the information for “Tower” was a six-year project, starting in 2006 before production began in 2012. Maitland said they wanted the film to include a variety of personal perspectives so viewers would identify with at least one of the characters’ stories.
“It was a real challenge deciding [which stories to use],” Maitland said. “You have to learn everything you can about the subject matter before making those big decisions, because you don’t want to regret leaving out something.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tower” depicts its eye-witness stories with rotoscope animation, a technique that uses footage of real actors overlaid with painted colors, rather than pure live action. Maitland said the decision was made partially out of necessity because he knew UT would not allow the crew to reenact the events on campus with actors, guns and blood, but it was also a way for the film to appeal to younger audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We wanted high school and college kids to see themselves reflected on that screen,” Maitland said. “[In the film], we are looking at young innocent people going through the events of that day, not as the memories from 50 years ago, but as a visceral first-hand experience with immediacy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture made its debut at this year’s South By Southwest film festival, where it won the Grand Jury Prize and the Audience Award for best documentary feature, and is set for a theatrical release on Oct. 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maitland said he hopes “Tower” can push forward a dialogue about gun violence at a time when mass shootings have become increasingly common. To help start this conversation, the crew plans to host screenings at college campuses across the nation later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the picture portrays a dark moment in UT’s history, producer Megan Gilbride said “Tower” is not meant to frighten viewers by remembering the tragedy, but is instead intended to highlight the strength and heroism of many involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today, when we watch these events unfold, it’s hard not to be beaten down by what feels like the monsters that we’re seeing,” Gilbride said. “The story that ‘Tower’ is telling is really about the amazing humanity and the sacrifice and caring that strangers felt for each other. I think we can see our better selves in those people.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Tower-Movie.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Tower-Movie.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>tower</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thomas Karr, 24</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;victim-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/ThomasKarr.png&quot; alt=&quot;Thomas Karr&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Illustration by Jacky Tovar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Ray Karr was a Latin American studies senior and a member of the U.S. Army from 1962 to 1965.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was born in Dickens County, Texas. Karr was shot through the spine as he was walking back to his residence hall after completing a Spanish exam. Karr died later that day in the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karr was survived by his mother and father, Royce Blackwell Karr and Ray T. Karr, a brother who was a student at Texas Tech, Don Karr, and a sister, Mrs. Joe Moore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karr is buried in Dickens County, Texas at Spur Cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Thomas-Karr.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Thomas-Karr.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>victim</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thomas Eckman, 18</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;victim-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/ThomasEckman.png&quot; alt=&quot;Thomas Eckman&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Illustration by Jacky Tovar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Frederick Eckman, a freshman studying anthropology, and his eight-month-pregnant girlfriend, Claire Wilson, were having coffee together on campus shortly before the shooting. As they began to head back to their car, Wilson was shot in the stomach. Eckman called out to Wilson and reached over to her, but then was shot outside Benedict Hall. Eckman died later in the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His fiancee’s unborn child died during an emergency surgery performed on Wilson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was survived by his mother, Mary Louise Eckman, his father, Frederick Eckman, and a half-brother, Michael R. Campbell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his memory, the Thomas F. Eckman Special Collections Division of Bowling Green State University’s Library was established. Eckman was from Spain but buried in Ottawa, Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Thomas-Eckman.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Thomas-Eckman.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>victim</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thomas Ashton, 22</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;victim-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/ThomasAshton.png&quot; alt=&quot;Thomas Ashton&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Illustration by Jacky Tovar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Ashton was a recent graduate of the University of California visiting Austin for Peace Corps training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ashton was on his way to meet with fellow trainees at the Student Union when he heard sudden noises and saw bodies falling to the ground. Exiting the UT Computation Center, Ashton looked toward the west side of the tower and was shot in the chest. Ashton died in Brackenridge Hospital soon after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ashton is buried at Hillside Memorial Park in Redlands, California.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Thomas-Ashton.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Thomas-Ashton.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>victim</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Former Texan reporters recall covering Whitman shooting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/staffers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Texan Staffers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Photo by Daily Texan Staff&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Economidy, editor-in-chief of The Daily Texan, gathered staff members at 9 a.m. on Aug. 1, 1966 for an impromptu meeting to plan the next day’s newspaper. Like many summer days, news was dull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What we need,” someone said, “is something like the Rigsby-Stark murders.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous summer, James C. Cross confessed to raping and killing Susan Rigsby and murdering Shirley Stark, both 21-year-old coeds from Dallas. The Texan covered the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone else chimed in, “Why doesn’t someone go up and jump off the tower?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we all agreed,” Economidy said, “that would be a great news feat.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in three hours, 25-year-old architectural engineering student Charles Whitman would go to the top of the UT Tower, kill 13 people and injure 32, after murdering his mother and wife. The staff, as student journalists, would be responsible for covering America’s first mass shooting on a college campus. Their newsroom would become the on-campus press headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meeting ended and staffers dispersed. Economidy headed back toward his apartment in West Campus for lunch, listening to the radio while he ate. Around noon, he heard KTBC anchor Neal Spelce on the radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is a warning to the citizens of Austin,” Spelce said. “Stay away from the University area. There is a sniper on the University Tower firing at will.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economidy ran toward campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Texas was the first.  Fifty years after Whitman mounted his arsenal on the observation deck of the Tower, the list of school shootings has added, among others, Columbine, Virginia Tech and Sandy Hook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the pattern that follows school shootings today — the shock, the grief, the memorializing and the forgetting — didn’t happen then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This was in 1966,” Senator Judith Zaffirini said. “It wasn’t at a time when mass shootings were, unfortunately, as common as they have become. It was a totally different phenomenon. It was mind-boggling.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nation was flummoxed. A region was shaken. How could that happen here? Austin was not the metropolis it is now. There were about 700,000 fewer people. The Capitol and the UT Tower were the two tallest buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zaffirini was the special editions editor for the Texan that summer. She sat at her desk on the south side of the journalism building, in front of a window with a perfect view of the tower when the shooting began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she heard the first gun shots at 11:48 a.m., she thought it was construction. She headed to the Student Union for lunch, walking out in the open and in range, still hearing the bangs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But never, ever, ever, did I consider it was gunfire,” Zaffirini said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She walked up to the entrance, through a huddle of students, and into the normally packed dining area. Empty. She grabbed orange juice and walked past the entrance, through the huddle of students again, and headed back to the journalism building. A man suddenly tackled her from behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Don’t you know what’s going on?” he asked her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What’s going on?” she replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When sports writer Michael Lonsford got out of his class around 11:45,  he walked to the tower, to the ground floor vending machines. Guns fired. Bodies fell. Students ran. But Lonsford kept walking. Once inside, he found out someone was shooting people from the observation deck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Lonsford was stuck inside the tower, Zaffirini was now inside the Student Union along with managing editor Virgil Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zaffirini tried using a payphone to reach her husband. They shared a car and he was scheduled to give her a ride home. He was going to pick her up at the journalism building, meaning he would drive on the Drag, where Whitman killed five people and injured four others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I remember the long, long, long lines of students trying to call out, trying to call home, trying to call other people to say they were OK,” Zaffirini said. “And I wanted to call my husband to tell him not to come because I knew he wouldn’t know what was going on. How would he?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She finally reached him, and he was stunned to find out what was going on. She told him to stay home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Union, she saw people injured and killed on the Drag. She heard shots. Shouts. Screaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a war zone,” Zaffirini recalled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Covington has always had bad eyesight. He has a degenerative retinal disease, and his vision was was 2400, 1/100th of healthy vision.
He was at his apartment when the shooting started, and despite the risk, the distance and his vision, he decided to head to campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was a 22-year-old Daily Texan staffer,” said Covington, the editorial page editor, “and I wasn’t going to be left out of this story.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He ran from his apartment on Nueces, to the Drag, to the UT News and Information Center by the Littlefield House, then hid behind a parked car by the journalism building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Covington hid behind a car, Economidy was on the Drag, by the United Methodist Church on 24th and Guadalupe Streets, directing traffic away from the drag and diverting them to side streets. Suddenly, someone was shot several feet from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He ran to the journalism building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covington knew he needed to get inside, and he sort of saw the south entrance to the journalism building, but everything was a blur; his eyes didn’t allow him to make out sharp edges or separate colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He furiously ran to the door through wide-open space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once inside, he walked toward his office, and noticed Norris Davis, Chairman of the School of Journalism, and other students, holding open the front door and looking up at the Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You idiots are going to get yourselves shot if you don’t get away from that door,” Covington yelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They shut the door and backed away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Get off your butts. Get out there and win the Pulitzer Prize,” Economidy told two photographers, sitting inside the journalism building, peeping through the blinds up at the tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economidy then grabbed a notepad and rushed down to the UT campus police, located on 24th street and Speedway. Once he arrived, UT campus chief of police Allen R. Hamilton told him, “John get me a phone number out of the phone directory of an armored car service.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The armored car met them at the Texas Memorial Museum and was used as an ambulance. Hamilton and another officer rode inside, while Economidy rode on the outside of the vehicle, scribbling notes on his pad as the armored car picked up victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, at about 1 p.m., Hamilton turned to Economidy and said, “Hot damn John, they got him, let’s go.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The massacre lasted 96 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwward, Economidy returned to the Texan office. Lonsford was assigned, along with Lucy Horton, to go the hospital and interview the wounded, but no one wanted to talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Economidy waited inside the tower. The victims were brought down, uncovered and in gurneys standing straight up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He only caught a glimpse of Whitman, peppered by three shotgun blasts, since Hamilton told him to leave as they brought him down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later that day, reporters were allowed to go up to the tower. Covington, the ediotorial page editor, went up and was struck by the nauseating smell of blood that had pooled up in the reception area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It smelled like raw meat,” Covington recalled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went to the observation and peered out the north side of the tower, looking down at the journalism building, the car he hid behind and the space he ran through. “I could hit myself with a rock,” he thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That was the first time I felt weak on my knees,” he recalled, thinking if he could see himself, then a former Marine with Sharpshooter’s badge could’ve seen him too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Texan, Johnson worked with the photo department to choose a photo. Economidy designed the paper, choosing to use a four-column spread and banner headline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lonsford went home and watched Walter Cronkite discuss the shooting. Zaffirini went home with her husband as well, still so shaken by the shooting that she waited outside the bathroom door as her husband showered, not wanting to be alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UT Tower stretches 307 feet into the Austin sky, a landmark of the school, but a reminder of the darkest day in its 133-year history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 50 years, Judith Zaffirni is startled by the sound of construction. The impact and the memories from Aug. 1, 1966 cannot be forgotten. Time helps repress them. George Covington has only thought of that day two or three times. Virgil Johnson has forgotten a lot from that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the office, behind the computer, on the wall, hangs a plaque. Every Texan editor gets to choose an issue of the Texan during their regime to be copper encrusted as a plaque. The paper John Economidy chose is the front page from Aug. 2, 1966.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He didn’t want to forget.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Texan-Reporters.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Texan-Reporters.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>texan</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Roy Schmidt, 29</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;victim-img&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/RoySchmidt.png&quot; alt=&quot;Roy Schmidt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Illustration by Jacky Tovar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roy Dell Schmidt worked for the Electrical Distribution Department. He was born in Manor, Texas. He was working on campus and was in the process of making a call when he was informed of the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was struck in the stomach as he and a co-worker fled toward their truck. He died within minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was survived by his parents, Theo and Edna Schmidt, and his brother, Wayne Schmidt, as well as his wife Nancy and their
daughter Kimberly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Roy-Schmidt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Roy-Schmidt.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>victim</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Survivor recalls confusion, terror of Tower shooting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/rolandehlke.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roland Ehlke&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;byline-photo&quot;&gt;Photo Courtesy of Roland Ehlke&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1966, Roland Ehlke was in Austin preparing to leave for Iran with the Peace Corps. On August 1, he was headed to lunch with Tom Herman and David Mattson to meet the other volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the shooting began, they didn’t realize it was gunfire — Ehlke said they assumed it was fireworks or construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When I was shot, I had no idea,” Ehlke said. “There was street work going on, and I thought something maybe had gone awry there. We didn’t know what was happening.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yells erupted just as Ehlke realized he’d been shot in the arm. The same bullet also struck his friend. Around them, Ehlke noticed people beginning to fall on the sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“After a while, it became clear it wasn’t an accident, but there was still confusion,” Ehlke said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were trying to seek shelter in a jewelry store when Ehlke said a bullet hit Mattson’s wrist. While trying to help him, Ehlke was shot once again. Even after making it into the safety of the store, a bullet came through the glass and shot the owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We thought, maybe they’re coming in here for jewelry,” Ehlke said. “We heard noises behind, too —  people who were shooting up at the Tower. We realized at this point there was a shooting, but it seemed like maybe there was a gunfight.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the three young men escaped by climbing out the back and over the fence to the alley, where an ambulance was already waiting. Ehlke said that even their ambulance driver was hit trying to get around to the front of the building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ehlke said they didn’t know a man had been shooting from the Tower until they arrived at the hospital. Although his week-long hospitalization caused him to miss out on his trip to Iran, he later recovered, and travelled to Afghanistan with the Peace Corps instead, still sporting bandages on his arm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ehlke later became a pastor, and today, he teaches classes on religion, English and literature at Concordia University. He said certain things from that hot summer day in 1966 are still so vivid in his memory that it hardly feels like 50 years have passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My life has been very blessed with children and grandchildren,” Ehlke said. “But I still think back on one of our friends, Tom [Ashton], who was shot and killed that day. It made me realize that life is brief, and you never know when it will end. Every day is a gift.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Roland-Ehlke.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://dailytexanonline.com/features/tower/Roland-Ehlke.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>survivor</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
